Yo,
I hope you all can hear me. Um, oh, I
got some people jumped in already.
Jim Ori, what's up, man? It's been
forever.
Big UNK, man. You've been a while. Um,
can you all hear me? Somebody out there,
give me some
some love. If uh
if you can hear me,
I'm going to figure out in a second how
to
get old Dan Garner joined in.
Oh, thank you, buddy. All right. I
appreciate it. Okay, you got good audio.
Oh, Cody, I forgot to block you. Damn. I
guess I'll let you stay in here.
All right, we'll let that joker stay in
here.
Um,
cool. How in
how do I add Dan? You can obviously tell
I think this is my first time ever doing
an Instagram live.
Uh,
any help out there, friends? Do I have
to ask ask Dan or do uh let's see how's
that work?
Um,
let's see.
Aha.
Oh, there's the man himself, I think.
What's going on? Hey,
what's up, buddy?
Okay, can you hear me loud and clear?
Oh, wait. No.
Are you there? Yeah, I should be. Okay,
I got you. I got you. I got you. Good
now. Can you hear me?
Yeah. I bet you I think we got a little
delay because you're coming all the way
from the Arctic Circle. So
yeah, Canada's the active circle. What's
up, my man? How you doing? Good, man.
We're going to have to uh assume there's
a little bit of lag time here, so we'll
do our best not to talk over each other.
Yeah. Yeah, that happens. But uh we'll
just answer questions and then I'll try
and not yell about things, which
certainly will happen. We'll just we'll
see how it goes. D. I was going to wait
a few minutes, but there's a truckload
of people already in here. So, I see no
reason to get going. So, um, cool. So,
those of you out there, friends, thank
you for the questions that you put up on
on Twitter and, um, Instagram and and
Facebook and stuff. So, um, we got a ton
actually, like way more than I was
anticipating. So, um, we've cured them
just a little bit and we've got a bunch
we're going to try to run through. Um,
so Dan and I go back and forth, but
before we do that, just really quickly,
um, I'm going to give you a little bit
of background real quick about myself
and what I do and then Dan as well. So
Dan, why don't you just anyone who's not
familiar with you, just tell them, you
know, your background that's pertinent
to today's discussion. Sure. So you
guys, I'm a functional medicine
practitioner. Um, so I've got a ton of
theoretical knowledge in this world. I'm
also just this is my absolute number one
passion. This is all I think about. Andy
actually called me earlier today and I
was reading a study on uric acid. So,
it's just kind of gives you an insight
on the kind of person I am. Um, it
doesn't matter what enzyme, what
chemical reaction, what's going on in
the body. I'm interested in it. I find
biology unbelievably fascinating. So,
I've got a formal education in health
science and functional medicine. But
more importantly, I think it is more
important. I've got experience in this
world. So I combined that theoretical
knowledge with literally having done
over a thousand labs on people and labs
on high performance athletes, obese
people, bodybuilders. Uh you name the
type of demographic. I'm getting
attacked by my dog. You name the type of
demographic. I've got experience working
with them. When you do labs on over a
thousand people, you end up seeing
things that sometimes you just won't
find in scientific journals and making
decisions that work that become your own
KPIs that are really ahead of the curve.
So, I'm a guy who's trained uh three
Super Bowl champions, an Olympic gold
medalist, an Olympic silver medalist,
two Olympic bronze medalist, two UFC
World Title winners, two WWE champions,
player of the year winners. I mean, you
name it. I'm uh I'm the coach guy here.
So, I've got a lot of experience and uh
my dogs attacking me and I can hear a
kid in your background. So,
that's where we're at. But I think
that's uh that's all I feel socially
awkward talking about myself. So, I'll
just leave that there. Dope. Cool.
You've also got uh as as one of our
friends here pointed out in the comments
section and your clever green shirt.
You've got u one of your athletes you've
been working with for a number. year.
Sean Omali is competing this weekend.
Yeah. So, um, good luck. Uh, you know
what's funny is actually I had, um, in
my time hop, I had a picture pop up of
Sean and I in bed together like 5 years
ago. Really? Yeah. I was like, man, I
should post this right now cuz he's
fighting this weekend. And then I
thought, he's baby Sean, right? He's
just before all the colors and it's a
little baby fro. And we were in a hotel
a hotel room. when we were in a bed
together um in Fresno, California. So
hilarious. Good dude. Good dude. Um
cool. So, you know, most of you probably
know me, but in case you don't, um I'm a
full-time professor and scientist. I've
got a PhD in human bioenergetics, and
for the last over decade, I've been
running the Center for Sport Performance
at Cal State Fullerton. So, we do
science and research in anything that we
feel like is going to enhance human
performance or has the potential to. Um,
and on the side, I've I've been working
with professional athletes like Dan for
a long time. So, a number of combat
sport athletes. Same idea. I'm not going
to run through it, but it would sounds,
you know, akin to Dan's list there. Lots
of world champions and the highest paid
player and multiple major American
sports um are close MVP saw young award
winners like things. So, that's not to
say Dan and I are the smartest or best
guys in the room, but um the reason we
want to get on this and do this little
live today is number one, just to see if
you guys have an appetite for it. Are
you guys interested in hearing and
seeing these things? Um and then just to
talk about some of the stuff that we
found in our experience with the elite
athletes. Um so, just to qualify then,
um we're not going to talk anything
about disease diagnosis or treatment or
management. you know, both of I have
done that. Both D and I have done that a
little bit in the past, but really today
we want to talk about the other end of
the spectrum, which is what we're most
uh qualified for. So, um let's just jump
right into it. So, sort of the first
question I thought we would tackle and
and somebody um Sammy here has already
asked us here, but the basic thing you
want to optimize performance, you aren't
really super worried about your
cholesterol levels or, you know,
thinking that you're going to die
anytime soon. So, um just to start off,
uh Dan, what are the what are the labs?
Um just oh sorry last we're going to
keep this just a blood work. There's so
many other areas we could go to but for
the sake of our time here we're just
going to stick to blood analysis for a
variety of reasons. So just a what what
are the blood labs? What are they
called? How do they ask for them? What
do they ask for um that you typically
want your high performance athletes to
start with? Sure. So that's an awesome
awesome question. And I love that we're
sticking with just blood work because
blood work has an unbelievable amount of
scientific literature on. I look, I'll
tell you guys when something's my
opinion. I speak from the evidence. So I
always say this is my opinion if uh if
it's not directly from the evidence. And
when it comes to blood work, there is so
much evidence in this world. If you ask
your doc for a CBC and a CMP,
they're going to know exactly what you
mean right away. That's a complete blood
count and a comprehensive metabolic
panel. Those two labs are so
unbelievably underrated. It's it's it's
staggering what you can draw. I mean a
lot of people think like how do I
measure hydration? What should I do with
hydration? Um even just a basic basic
lab um you can get there's something
called osmalerity. Osmalarity sounds
fancy but it's really not. It just means
there's a lot of things on one side and
not much on this side. So your body will
diffuse things to that other side to
make it even. There's calculations we
can draw from basic blood chemistry to
give us serum osmalerity which is the
number one gold standard measure for
intracellular osmalerity. So we can get
the best hydration marker possible by
calculating very simple things from
labs. So when people look at bloods and
they just see okay this is normal normal
normal at a range they they don't
actually understand that ratios are
actually more important than a lot of
these actual markers and then the way in
which you combine different things to
get osmalerity to get nonin gap to get
all of these different um blood
viscosity markers there's so much that
we can draw from that that a skilled eye
is not just looking for a state of
disease when you look at these things
you can 100% enhance performance,
enhance health, enhance adaptation from
training. So that's really just what I
would open with. Get a CBC, get a CMP,
and it's not the lab that gets you the
value, it's the interpreter of the lab
that's going to get you the value. Bring
that to the right person and they will
make you a different athlete.
Yeah. Awesome. So, a little bit more
context on that. Those labs are fairly
cheap, too. Depending on where you're
at, most likely your insurance is going
to cover both of those. But most likely,
they're not standard either. So, if you
go and just say, "I just want some lab
work," they're probably going to order
lipid panel, maybe a few other things.
But, if you just say those two uh
phrase, those two terms, you'll probably
get them probably uh you know, you
probably get them free or close to it.
Um, if you're a student at most American
universities, those will also probably
come with your health care packages. um
free to your students or very small $10
upgrades or things like that. So um that
is is what we order and
what we typically do for most
individuals is if we see something in
those labs that indicates a possibility
of something else, then we will go
directly measure those things. So if we
see something there that indicates, hey,
maybe copper's off or we think there's
something going on in another location,
then we'll go over those those labs
outside of that. Um, now for our high
performance athletes, sometimes we just
kind of order everything at once, but
um, it just saves time and you know, and
a lot of that too comes down to um,
understanding that reference ranges
don't mean a whole lot. So,
I know so this is this is where we're
going to go next and there's actually a
couple of questions in the comments
section alluded to this. Perfect. Um,
and so yeah, this is the one thing and
so there's comments about sort of
um, you know, which ratios matter. you
said ratios matter which ones do and
then what are the reference range values
so if I guess the way to open this part
of the conversation is you have to
understand everyone where these
reference ranges come from number one
it's not one set standard so depending
on where you get your blood labs from
which laboratory lab quest or or labcore
or quest or your physician what's in the
right reference range could be different
right and and we can certainly go over
some examples if you want within that
though there's arguments in among what's
what are those reference ranges actually
telling you? And so if you're going to a
physician and ordering blood work, all
they're really looking for are do you
have any major flags for disease?
And if you don't have any of those,
they're basically going to move on. Um
obviously our goal this in in this talk
is to do something a little bit
different. So uh anything you want to
add on that before we start maybe
talking about some details, Dan? Of
course. Yeah. I mean, and I'll keep it
short because I think you know how long
I could talk about reference ranges for,
but just to give you guys kind of an
insight onto on what we're looking at.
Um, kind of the question was kind of
jumped into ratios plus reference
ranges. In terms of what ratios matter,
I mean, there's excellent longevity
research with respect to having a total
cholesterol to triglyceride measure of
approximately 2:1. So, someone could
have an slightly elevated cholesterol
and triglyceride, yet if the ratio holds
true, it's not nearly as impactful as
what somebody may think it is. Um,
another good one that really flies
against what a lot of people think is
that your LDL should be at a 2:1 ratio
to your HDL. If your HDL is higher than
your LDL, that's actually dysipidemia.
That's a problem. You've got a
pathological state. Everyone's trying to
drive HDL up as high as possible, but
there's excellent research that HDL when
you get above 80 increases risk for
cancer. So ratio with LDL, everything
there's no like good and bad. Everything
has its own physiological function. And
so long as it's working in concert with
the other things that regulate it,
that's what's going to be really
important. Um, you'll find uh uh white
blood cell counts as well on blood on
blood panels. You're going to find your
your neutrfils, your lymphosytes, your
monocytes, your eosinaphils, your
basophils. And with respect to them,
they should be at 60 30730.
That's basically the percentage
breakdown. But that's the thing. It's a
percentage. It's not the absolute
amount. So you're looking at ratios. If
your ratio of neutrfils to lymphosytes
is closer to one one that actually
indicates a viral infection in the body
and it could be asymptomatic and that's
a one one indicating viral but if we
have uh it's actually research has shown
that if you're getting two to one
lymphosy to uh sorry neutrfil to
lymphosy and then especially higher it
indicates a bacterial infection and how
many people Andy have we seen with
bacterial problems in their stools.
Yeah. Unbelievable. So, it kind of
tailor back to what you said when um if
when we're looking at this, it can also
tell us what else we should order or
what else we would order to look at. If
somebody's neutrfil to lymphosy was
slightly off, we know, okay, you
probably should get a stool analysis.
We're going to look more into this
thing. So with respect to ratios,
reference ranges, I could go on all day.
But just because you're normal in the
reference range says absolutely nothing
about your current physiologic state.
Yeah, I have seen a number of people in
my life with an HDL or over 80 like you
mentioned. Um certainly a handful over
85. Not one of them has been healthy.
No, never once. Never once. It certainly
won't. And then like there are other
markers too like if you're if you're
looking at inflammation for example on a
basic blood chemistry GGT uric acid and
Billy Rubin are your absolute best
markers. Uric acid for it's a water
soluble antioxidant. Billy Rubin's a fat
soluble antioxidant. So you get a more
complete picture. And then GGT
represents glutathione status in the
body. So we're getting a total look at
inflammatory states in the body. So if
one of these markers is off, then we
know, okay, you know, maybe I should
actually look elsewhere to see what the
root cause of this inflammation status
is. Yeah. The fun part about that Oh,
sorry. Go ahead. No, you No, go ahead. I
say the fun part about those three
markers in particular is it gives you a
little bit of directionality of where to
go as well. 100%. Yeah. And it's uh and
it's fun for us. I love when I look at
that blood chemistry that's all messed
up because that's actually I don't like
back in the day back in the 50s doctors
only had like high blood pressure and
type two diabetes that was it be real
easy to do practice back then but now I
love looking at I messed up blood
chemistries because we've learned so
much about biology yeah actually I
probably should have said this at the
beginning but I want to take a quick
pause here we're only on question one by
the way folks I got at least eight or
nine more so I'm going to speed up the
pace a little bit. But um
Dan, I'll let you answer this for
yourself, however you practice, but for
me personally
um you know, I' I've been looking at
athletes blood panels for a long time,
over a decade, um have a decent
experience in this field. And what I
still say is as you're going through
this, make sure you're tying blood
chemistry to subjective outcomes as
well. In other words, um you are still
treating a human. You're still treating
an athlete. So you want to look at these
blood markers and say hey am I seeing
num a number of signs that point to
something that may be even asymatic
asymptomatic. That's important. But also
you have to ask them how are you
feeling? Um what are your performance
measures looking like? How's our
recovery? Are we getting better? Do we
have any other signs and symptoms? Are
you sick all the time? Um trouble
sleeping. This is the stuff that really
ties it in. And when you see something
in the blood that then matches
symptomology that you're hearing from
the individual, you've got a very very
strong indication that that is a true
finding and not a false positive or a
false negative. So always keep that in
mind. As much as I do love to see the
blood stuff and go bing bing bing, we're
seeing the signs of um yeah,
inflammation is excessively high or
you're uh immuno compromised or whatever
else is going on. You still really need
to make sure you're taking everything
else into consideration. Um because
there is a lack there's always a lack of
science no matter what right there's
there none of these things are 100%
established because there's too much
variation from person to person there's
too much variation from laboratory to
laboratory none of these things so so
there there are some rightful criticism
of any marker but the point is what
we're looking for are trends that link
up in multiple areas so we're seeing the
same thing with your data metrics we're
seeing the same thing with what you're
reporting and we're seeing this in your
blood it starts to form a really strong
case so this This is why it's important
that you spend time with your athlete or
your your individual and ask other
questions and don't just take labs, send
out supplements. That that's not the
best practice um you're ever going to
have. So, totally. I I actually just did
this a couple of days ago with a with a
professional bodybuilder. He I just
shared my screen and he showed me his
labs and I went through his labs and I
started talking about what the labs are
and then he was actually, "Hey, I'm
actually feeling that. Hey, I'm actually
seeing that. We actually kind of met in
the middle as I was unpacking his labs.
His symptoms were like, "Hey, this is
exactly where I'm at." So then we then
had a perfect diagnostic case to move
forward and order more direct labs to
find the true root cause to his problem.
So totally, man, subjective and
objective is really the science and art
of coaching. Oh, okay. Awesome. Um, I'm
going to jump over to we're going to
take some uh viewer questions here in a
second, but I want to jump over to one
of the ones. Um, there's a handful of
you that basically sent us your full
labs. We're like, "Hey, interpret
can't quite nail that." Um, but do do
you want to handle Dan that second one
that's pretty lengthy? I don't know if
you want to skip over that or some parts
of that. The second one we've got on our
uh list here. Yeah. So, I'll handle it,
but just everybody already understands
that context matters. So, I don't know
this guy's diet. I don't know his
genetic predispositions. I don't know
things, but I can absolutely tell you
what I know based on the numbers you
give me. Cool. Let's do that. So, you
want me to read off the question and
then you can give us your thoughts on
it? Let's do it. Okay. Um, so this is
Michael Godwin number nine here said,
uh, he was he's a powerlifting athlete
basically and he recently had some blood
work done. Uh, the results showed his
thyroid function, particularly free tea,
was high at 26.6. 6 uh pom moles per
liter. In addition, his liver alt was
classified as high at 65. CK was 683 and
ura 9.2, creatinine 113, and um globulin
36.3. So, I jumped some units there, but
it's because I know what they are and I
know you know they're at you're looking
at the same thing. Um you guys can go
look if you want, but yeah. So, what are
your thoughts there? It's pretty
actually. So that that one's actually
kind of cool for people to to hear
about. So his his high tea was high T4,
I'm assuming. Yeah. So I thought so
because his ALT is high. So here's how
this work. Yeah. Yeah. So here here's
how this works. This guy has high T4
which represents actually a lot of
states of anxiety because you're
producing a lot of thyroid hormone. What
a lot of people don't know and which is
why it's important to understand
functional physiology and not just a
recipe book. A lot of people have a
recipe book approach to labs like high
cholesterol do this low GDT do this this
that doesn't work. You have to
understand the metabolic pathway at
which that lab has arrived at that
result. That's how you truly interpret a
lab at the highest level. And this guy
having a high T4 that represents I says
a little overactive metabolism
represents a little bit of anxiety. A
lot of people don't know this guy also
had high globulin. So there's two main
proteins. There's two main proteins in
the blood. Albamin and globulin. Albamin
wasn't high but globulin was globulin
actually requires 10 times more
elptophan for the body to manufacture
than albamin. So whenever somebody's
making a ton of globbulin, they're
actually utilizing a ton of elptophan.
And when you're using a lot of
elptophan, tryptophan is actually the
precursor for both serotonin and
melatonin. And serotonin helps promote
feelings of positivity and calmness.
Melatonin, everybody's already familiar
with helps you sleep. And as a memory
tool, serotonin puts you to sleep.
Melatonin keeps you asleep. But if
globbulin's eating up all of your
tryptophan and you have thyroid driving
up anxiety levels, well then that's
somebody who's going to be a lot more
predisposed to anxiety at this point in
time. Now T4 could also be high due to a
liver dysfunction because our body it'll
actually when you're looking at thyroid
values in a lab, 93% is T4 and only 7%
is the active T3. T4 doesn't actually
convert um it's it's kind of like on an
as needed basis you can think about it
T4 will convert to T3 to activate
metabolic processes but this conversion
happens in the gut bacteria the liver
and the mitochondria so his ALT was high
indicating liver damage which is
indicating an improper conversion over
to from T4 to T3 which is resulting in a
T4 buildup not to mention liver Liver
damage is what drives glabbulin up.
Yeah. So with this case, it's it's like
almost like a perfect case study for us
to show that I would exactly be looking
at liver issues because liver damage
drives up globulin. Liver damage would
inhibit conversion from T4 to T3. And
also him being a powerlifter, his
creatinin, his creatine kynise, those
things, those are going to be high
anyways because he's heavily muscled and
training hard. So I ain't even worried
about those. That's another good example
of being out of the reference range
doesn't mean it's representative of your
physiology. So I would be looking at the
co-actors for ALT such as magnesium and
B6. So that can actually function
better. And I'd also be looking at liver
health in general to see what's going
on, what's the blockage, where's the
damage coming from. And that would come
from his questionnaire, his diet, and
these other things. Yep. So, just to
follow up a little bit on this one as
well, um we we've had this recently
actually on a case that we worked on
together, but just for a little context,
friends, the liver can handle quite an
ass whipping. It really can. Um other
organs can't. And so, if you're like,
"Oh my god, I don't want whoever this
this, you know, individual is to be
like, "Oh my god, I have liver failure."
Uh look, probably not. We have seen
values much much much higher than this.
like way higher and people just fine. So
you're not optimized. Um this could be
kind times higher. Yeah. That Yeah. Like
or not joking. Yeah. Put a digit on that
for sure. Yeah. Um so you're you're in a
case spot. The other thing that we would
do is is if we were working with you, we
would target those things. We maybe do
some follow-up labs specifically for the
liver. Um we would do some all this
other stuff, questionnaires, but we
would also then I would probably have
you do a CO2 tolerance test. And um if
you want to look at Brian McKenzie and
Shift Adapt and those guys work, the CO2
tolerance test is also something we've
played with in our lab quite a bit. Um
and it seems to be a pretty good
indicator of someone's ability to handle
um state and trade anxiety. And so we
would look at this from the biochemistry
lab, all those things Dan just talked
about. Then but then we also look at
this from the other side of the
equation. So this is this really being
stress driven um or mitigated could it
be mitigated better by some higher
stress tolerance or is this something
totally physiological? because you're
not going to know. Remember, people are
complex and so you can't just look at
these things either from a oh you need
to meditate. Maybe maybe that's all the
dude needs. Maybe not though. Maybe we
need to medicate. Like there may be some
actual physiology we we've got to
correct. So we would look at this from
both sides of the equation to try to
understand. Maybe it's a little bit of
both. Maybe it's 8020. Maybe it's 100%
just uh hey stress tolerance issue. once
he calms down these things get back and
maybe something else is totally out of
wink out of out of whack as well that we
have to go address. So we'll call that
good there. Um I'm going to hop over to
to some of the questions and I'm like
obviously this is my first time so I'm a
little bit idiotic about scrolling
through the comments back to figure out
here. Um
lots of people jumping on here. There's
a lot of people that want us to
interpret their labs. I told you
bastards. I I warned you. I said we'll
do it. You throw them in there and now
y'all wait too late. We don't have time
now. Yeah. So, next time I throw up an
IG live here, you better hop in early
and we'll get to your stuff like we just
did this guy. Um, okay. There was
actually one question that's a bit off
target,
but we'll take it. Um, recommendations
for supplements for children uh and
kids. Uh, in general, my answer, I'm
sure, is the same as yours, Dan, which
is almost entirely unnecessary.
So, we'll keep this one really short. We
could elaborate a bunch, but the answer
is very simple. uh just almost surely
not something you need at that point.
Focus on the big rocks. Quality
movement, quality nutrition, food stuff,
and supplements are just almost
unnecessary
for sure. Do you want me to elaborate or
are you going to find the next one?
Yeah. No, I think we're good there. Um
uh recommended lab test frequency for
natural athletes.
Um, if you're a natural athlete and
you're not driving your body to the
extreme, I think twice per year is very
fair. I think once every six months is
is uh is a good frequency to have. But
if you are enhanced, it would be once
every four months would be the absolute
minimum. I prefer once every 3 months.
Yeah, I would say it depends also on uh
what we see initially. So if you look
pretty good and we have some minor
things to correct, six months is fine.
If we get in there though, and this is,
you know, happened many times, and you
see some gnarly stuff, you've got huge
like way double these, triple these
liver values, you've got kidney
dysfunction, and we've had this recently
um some pretty gnarly kidney signals on
someone who has to go through a pretty
extensive weight cut for sport. We
wanted to follow up 30 days later, every
30 days until we get correction on that.
Um so, let let the labs lead you a
little bit. Um it it depends on how
close uh how far away from competition
you are. Um as a standard for your
average person twice a year is probably
sufficient. I guess it's a good point to
talk about assuming nothing else is
wrong twice per year. Yeah. Um
you have to understand friends that like
minerals and vitamins and hormones tend
some of them are fast changing but most
are not. So if you take a bunch of
vitamin D for a week, you're probably
not doing much to your vitamin D status
in 7 days. It takes quite a long time to
change mineral status um to a
significant level. So doing anything in
less than 30 days for most of the things
you are concerned with or
um especially things are pretty good. If
things are completely uh deficient or
way too high, then they will autocorrect
pretty quickly, right? So it's a law of
a curve. So being way offkilter changes
fast, but as you get closer and closer
to normal, then changes happen much
slower. And so yeah, a lot of the times
even every six weeks would be like
that'd be pretty aggressive. Um probably
bordering on wasteful
more like Yeah, more like data
collection like it's almost research
instead of an like a protocol design at
that time.
Yeah. So, another question. Um, do we go
through MDs to order our labs or is
there other way to do that? Um, I'll
answer first and then you can go. So,
depending on the sport that you're in.
So, with Major League Baseball folks,
they tend to have a team doc or um NFL
guys, we have a team dock we can go
through for some things. Um, I can't
speak to NHL. Maybe you can. With the
UFC athletes, it's it's depending on
what we're going after. Sometimes it's
super easy for them to get labs orders,
sometimes not. But um my answer for this
is the vast majority of the time. We
just pay out of pocket. It's a couple of
hundred bucks. This is what they do for
a living. And they don't want to wait
two or three weeks for a guy to get they
just pay 200 bucks and get them done.
For sure. Yeah. So yeah, people can
actually go like if if you're frustrated
with an MD or whatever, you can actually
go it's great for Americans. They can go
to Alta Labs. Alta Labs you can order
whatever you want. So like you got Yeah,
I've used Alter Labs a truckload. Yeah,
it's super super super easy. So if
you're frustrated with someone then then
go through Alter Labs. But uh for
example, like going through myself or or
Andy, him and I, we do lab-based
nutrition and uh I'm a practitioner so I
get practitioner rates. So, if you hire
somebody who you should anyways, that's
the main point, uh, to look at your labs
for you. They're going to get you a
discount on your labs, plus you're going
to get the actual information. Yeah.
Yeah, that's the way to go. Um, the same
thing, I guess, while we're here, they
have a question about where to get your
labs done. It doesn't matter for the
most part. Um, that that part's fairly
irrelevant. The labs you order are what
matter and how they're interpreted. But
the person who actually sticks a needle
in your arm or the lab you send them to,
don't it's not that big a deal. Don't
worry about them too much. Um, what are
the most essential labs to get? We we
sort of covered that earlier, so you can
scroll back uh or go back to the
beginning if you want. Um, so let's hop
over to the kind of list of previous
questions.
Um, Daniel, your thoughts on chronic
just below reference range values for
WBC's and neutrfils? No other CBC
abnormalities.
So that's immune dysregulation. Yeah. So
that that's kind of Yeah. That goes back
to what I was saying previously. Your
neutrfil shouldn't be low. That
represents a viral load. So there
somebody and you guys everybody when it
comes to viruses, everybody wants to say
the C word these days. Viruses have been
around for decades. There's many of them
that uh that you can contract that will
throw off your labs that aren't the one
that everybody's talking about these
days that you can't even say on social
media anymore or else or else [__] goes
down. But um yeah, so if somebody has
chronically low white blood cells, you
can kind of imagine it like your white
blood cells would be really really high
in the presence of an acute problem. But
if they've been to war, you can imagine
them like you've sent soldiers to war
and now they've lost the war and now
you're losing your soldiers and now
they're chronically low because they've
lost the war and whatever infectious
state is currently in the body has won
and it's going to stay there. And the
percentages and the ratios are what's
going to tell you, hey, is it bacterial
based or is it viralbased? Uh what what
lab should we order? Um, if somebody has
chronically low white blood cells or uh
chronically low neutrfils, that to me
with no other information um represents
viral status within the body and would
uh would necessitate further
investigation through labs and
questionnaires.
Yep.
Yep. Bingo. Um, this is goes back to
that reference range. Yeah.
Conversation, right? Like you got to
know what you're looking at. Um, there's
a good one here in the chat. any good
books or articles or other resources um
that you can go to learn more about
CBC's and CMP interpretation?
Hey dude, you got to go to the
literature unfortunately. So I know
that's not the answer you want, but
there isn't an authority that's like
just giving all of the good stuff away.
That's actually well me and Andy kind of
sneak peek. We've been thinking about
doing a little uh a few presentations
across the USA in 2022. um not confirmed
but uh we we've been thinking about
doing it and uh basically that would be
the one to attend if it happens you know
if schedule permits between our athletes
and between our families we've got a
whole lot going on but um you really
have to go straight to the literature
and uh actually talked about this on
barbell shrugged I believe it was I
can't remember I think it was barbell
shrugged where uh there was actually an
excellent study came out from the
journal of insurance medicine that
showed that albiman should not be below
4.0. But you'll actually see on uh lab
corp that albiman the bottom end of the
range goes all the way down to 3.5.
Well, according to the journal of
insurance medicine, just a small study
involving 1.7 million people, by the
way, across 12 years of interpretation,
very small study, it actually showed
your mortality is going to increase over
200% if you drop below four. So like
when somebody's asking me, hey, how do I
identify optimal reference ranges? You
stay up to date with the literature and
uh unfortunately reading the literature
is really the only way to do that at
this point in time. So that that's
that's how it is. Yeah. The other reason
for that is um boy, I could pick a 100
examples of this. Remember science
science is not a a set thing. It
changes. And so
even things like vitamin D, if you're
paying attention to that literature, uh,
and there's been a handful of really
nice reviews in the last couple of years
published on this topic, um, it's a
strong likelihood that that's being
measured incorrectly. And so we're
getting a bunch of false information
there, but you wouldn't have you you
don't know. And so if you don't stay on
top of the research, um, you know, you
buy a iron. Geez. Yeah. Like another
Yeah. Uh, brutal. But, um, so, so you
really just need like if you want to get
really good at this stuff and really
want to service athletes, um, you're
just going to have to stay on top of the
research as much as you can. You're
going to miss some. That's fine. But,
um, do the best you possibly can to stay
on top of the research. There won't be a
a textbook um, that you can ever go back
to. So, that's a good one. Um, there was
actually a nice comment, a couple of
comments in here actually about uh,
inflammation.
And I do want to clarify a few things.
Um, yeah. So, when you're working with a
professional athlete, um, I I'm sorry, I
forgot who made this comment, but but
you're absolutely correct. Minimizing
inflammation is not always the goal. And
in fact, inflammation, uh, as you
astutely pointed out in your comment, is
the primary driver of adaptation. And
I've talked about this at length in many
other places, but you need to have, um,
again, this is why you don't want a
robot. You don't want just an app
interpreting your blood because
depending on the phase of training
you're in, the part of the year, the
part of your career, higher or lower
levels of some inflammation may be
totally appropriate. They may be in fact
the goal. So if you walk around all the
time minimizing inflammation, you again,
as you point out your comment, you could
be actually going against the thing. So,
this is why you need to have somebody
interpreting your labs or looking at
your labs carefully, paying attention to
you as an athlete, thinking about all
the other things in context. Um, if
you've got multiple draws over multiple
years and you can see what's normal for
you during this phase, um, then you're
going to make better decisions that way.
So, yeah, absolutely. None of this stuff
is interpreted just on its own. You have
to consider uh other factors as well.
So, I don't know if Dan, you have any
other additional comments to add to that
or the audience. Oh, man. I mean, I
could talk about inflammation for
freaking eight hours. So, it's a big
one. I The only thing I think I'd add is
a funny thing because when you called me
earlier, that uric acid study I was
reading, it was on inflammation. So,
what they actually did was they dunked a
bunch of college kids in ice cold tanks
and then the moment they got out of the
tank, so they measured the uric acid
before they got in the tank and then
they dunked them in the tank because who
cares about college kids? You could do
whatever you want with them. And then
they take them and they take them out of
the tank and they took their blood
instantly and uric acid was actually
extremely low because it was dealing
with the pro-inflammatory
beneficial horic response of that cold
plunge. So uric acid as the water
soluble antioxidant was actually being
triggered endogenously by the body to
deal with the free free radical release
of the cold plunge which I thought was
super cool. So the cold plunge
represents hormesis and an inflammation
you're trying to deal with and uric acid
represents a part of that endogenous
adaptation process of your body's
ability to strengthen the way in which
it deals with stressors. So just kind of
a cool full circle. I'm glad I read that
study now. Yeah, there was actually
another comment in here about uric acid.
Um
anything you feel like you want to say
about that or you want to just move on
to the next one? I know we're getting
real pressed for time here. So, yeah,
let's let's move on to the next one. Any
of these markers we could talk about
forever, brother. Yeah. Okay, cool.
There's a whole bunch of questions about
gut microbiome and digestion and things
like that, but um just for the sake of
time and to keep clarity here, uh I
guess if you're interested, maybe we'll
do another one of these and we'll pick a
different area of analysis. Um hormones
or uh sleep. There's a couple questions
about sleep analysis or or digestion. GI
stuff. Um, so if you all want to I guess
let us know um in some form or fashion
and perhaps we'll do this again. Um, you
seem to be getting a lot of
interactions. So this is great. I'm I'm
thrilled. Seems to be a lot of people
enjoying this. So yeah, perhaps. Thank
you guys for joining. Yeah, this is
good. Um, okay. So ah
try not to end the thing here. Not going
to hit the wrong button of my idiot
fingers.
So, let's see here. There was one I
wanted to go back with and fine.
Uh, okay, there it is. 52. Yeah.
Um, okay. We'll jump over
to maybe last couple questions here.
There's some pretty funny ones about
terrible experiences with physicians.
All right. We've been down this road.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Um
let's tackle maybe another really high
level one. Um someone wants to, you
know, people are super jazzed and
enraged about uh the anabolic side of
the equation. So they want to make sure
that they don't have low testosterone
and we actually see a lot of people
going on TRT probably unnecessarily
probably not a good thing actually maybe
even causing some problems with them.
But um if if we want to get a quick
glance at somebody's anabolic side of
the equation, um do you recommend
anything outside of what's going to come
in their traditional panels we talked
about or um what are you looking for
there? I guess only if it's low. So just
so many people have are quick to jump to
TRT if they have low testosterone. But I
never just think low testosterone, take
testosterone. I think low testosterone.
Why is it low? Because there are so many
different metabolic processes that could
represent an a logical explanation as to
why you have low testosterone that if we
solve those at the root causal level,
the testosterone can go back to what
it's normally functioning at, which is a
normal homeostatic level. Um, zinc and
magnesium are rate limiting steps in
testosterone synthesis. Vitamin D is
important for testosterone production.
um saturated fats and actually LDL
cholesterols are used to make anabolic
hormones. Uh certain heavy metals such
as arsenic and cadmium block
testosterone receptor sensitivity from
the leading cells from the brain on the
testes. So you can think about it like
the the brain wants to send LH and FSH
down to the testes in order to produce
sperm and testosterone respectively. But
cadmium and arsenic can cake up this
parking spot and simply just decrease
receptor activity on the on the testes.
Um environmental pollutants that the
exact mechanism is not known but they
are 100% endocrine disruptors and they
will uh offset testosterone. So if
somebody does have low testosterone and
the question was kind of doublefolded.
It's like testosterone, what's going on?
And um what labs would we order after?
It kind of depends on what their
questionnaire looked like at where I
would be leaning. Is it heavy metal? Is
it environmental fluid? Is it just
simply a micronutrient problem? Are they
not eating enough healthy fats? Um do
they have a stress problem? Because
cortisol has an antagonistic
relationship with testosterone. So if
they're pumping out too much cortisol,
they're not going to be making up
testosterone. you don't have low
testosterone, you have high cortisol.
And in this case, stress management can
actually reverse that. So there's a lot
of different routes we can take. Each of
them as important as the next. Yep. No
question about it. So I would say I
guess to summarize my position on that
is I'm not super concerned with which
metric you use to measure testosterone.
I'm more concerned with what you do
about it. Yeah. Yeah. Measured serum
testosterone. Serum testosterone is
scientifically fantastic. It gives us an
excellent indicator as to what's going
on. So, just a serum testosterone that
you can get in an endocrinology lab.
Just get your get your blood work done,
add it on top of your CBC and CMP for 20
freaking bucks and you're going to be
you're going to get an excellent
baseline to see where you're at. Yep.
Dope. Uh, somebody asked a nice question
there about Tonga Ali. So, I'm assuming
you guys were watching too much Andrew
Huberman right now. I know he's all over
it. Back in the day, we used to call
that Longjack. That's the name. You'll
hear it. Long Jack. That's Long Jack.
Yeah. Yeah. Totally. 100 to one. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's been around for
a long time. Um
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, there there's some
literature there. No question about it.
um you'll have plenty of people who will
talk about their own personal uh
experiences with it. But uh again, Dan
just sort of explained my position as
well and that which is like yeah can be
effective but um I haven't I just
haven't encountered honestly too many
people who who need that who that's the
best solution for. That's kind of the
thing, right? So does Tonata Ali or
Logjack does it work? Yes. Do you need
it? Well, let me let me reverse the
question. Is Tonka Ali gonna get rid of
arson?
Is Tona Ali going to get rid of your
psychological stress? You know, is you
know what I mean? So, yes, it is
efficacious, but it's only um
efficacious to its potential if a other
existing root cause problem is already
eliminated. So, if you have a
testosterone of 300, that's considered
normal. Tonka Ali can bring that
testosterone up. But if you have
existing stressors holding back your
physiology from being optimized, well
then you're never going to realize the
full potential of that herb despite the
literature behind it. Yeah. And I guess
just the last kind of comment here
before we wrap up. Um and just to
clarify, Andrew is a good friend of
mine, a very very good friend of mine.
So I'm just giving him the piss a little
bit here.
And a brilliant guy. I I talked to him
constantly. We're in very close
communication. So I knew him way back
before he had an Instagram. I promise.
So,
um, just a little little You knew him
back when it was long, Jack. Yeah,
for years. Um,
but yeah, you you sort of answered one
of the other questions in there, which
is what numbers are you looking for? Um,
and yeah, man, I would say the same
thing. I have seen people at 325, 350,
375 that are fine, that that are totally
outstanding. I've seen people at 600 who
feel like [__] Yeah. So, like it's only
one metric is an important one. It's the
one that kind of captures the zeicist
right now and it's it grabs attention.
But for for reference, I've worked with
a UFC world champion with a testosterone
and a 350. Yeah. Oh yeah. Yeah. So
imagine somebody who is [__] lean,
jacket, conditioned, absolutely
everything. So just make sure it's not
It is a thing, but it ain't the only
thing. Yeah. Cool. Well, we'll wrap
there up this based on time. you've got
uh dogs that need to get back to looking
your face and yeah, I've got children
and and other stuff to do. So, I hope
you all enjoyed that and I'll try to not
screw this up and save this and repost
this. So, I appreciate you all jumping
in. Again, let uh let myself and let Dan
know if you want us to do this another
time, if you want us if so, do you want
us to do blood again? Um or do you want
us to change topics? But uh yeah, we
won't know unless you speak up. So, hope
you enjoyed this. Peace out. Totally.
See you guys. Thanks, Dan. Yeah. How do
I end this thing? Do I hit the X? Is
that the best way? Um, probably.